So today's דף daf is דף מד, daf Mem Daled, and we
pick up at the bottom of מג עמוד ב. Mem Gimmel Amud
Bet. I should mention that כירה Kira is really, the פרק Perek
we're in the middle of, really
like a motherlode of key issues for
שבת. Shabbat. We did all of the דרבנן DeRabanans of
שבת, Shabbat, שהייה Shehiya and חזרה. Chazara. הטמנה Hatmanas coming up. We
did key aspects of the דאורייתא DeOraisa of בישול, Bishul, all the
דרבנן DeRabanans of בישול Bishul I meant, all key aspects of the
דאורייתא DeOraisa of בישול, Bishul, כלי שני, Kli Sheni, יד סולדת בו,
Yad Soledes Bo, בישול
חמה, Bishul Chama, בישול אור, Bishul Ur, and now we're in the
middle of a סוגיא Sugya which will take us to the with
the continuing משניות Mishnayot to the end of the פרק Perek about
major, probably one of the major sort of central discussions of מוקצה.
Muktzah. So you consider that you got דאורייתא DeOraisa and דרבנן DeRabanans
of שבת Shabbat and מוקצה Muktzah all in כירה, Kira, that's a
major,
you know, that's a major locus for for so much of what
is, you know, about what, you know, what is relevant for us
for
שבת. Shabbat. Question? Yes.
You said דאורייתא DeOraisa of מוקצה?
Muktzah? No, did I? I meant to say דאורייתא DeOraisa and דרבנן
DeRabanan of בישול Bishul and the and also מוקצה. Muktzah. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. So now we had a debate about what happens if
you've got a dead body in the yard. We got onto this
discussion because of the position that you can only carry something for
the sake of a non-מוקצה Muktzah object, so what do you do
to protect a dead body? And then we got into speaking about
how do you move the dead body? And they allowed you if
you put an infant or a loaf of bread on it to
move it, which is a major exception because normally that idea putting
היתר heter on something is when you have like a, like you
know, a tray which you keep the candlesticks on so that the
tray shouldn't only be a בסיס, basis, a base for the candlesticks,
you also make it a בסיס basis for the loaf of bread.
But here the מת, meis, the corpse, is itself obviously מוקצה. Muktzah.
So to allow you to move it for its own sake because
because sort of with this fiction that there is a, you know,
because of the loaf of bread it's like you're moving the loaf
of bread, that's a major allowance, but everybody agrees to that. And
then the debate came if you don't have the loaf of bread
or the infant, can you move the מת meis indirectly מן הצד
Min HaTzad by sort of like turning it from bed to bed?
And that was a debate and that's the issue of טלטול מן
הצד Tiltul Min HaTzad which we are going to wrap up. I
see there's some questions but let me just let's read a little
bit and finish this and then I'll take some questions. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: כי פליגי, Ki Pligi, it's four lines
before the lines get wide, כי פליגי Ki Pligi so when do
they disagree? דלית
ליה, D'Leis Lei, that there's no infant or loaf of bread. מר
סבר Mar Savar טלטול מן הצד שמיה טלטול, Tiltul Min HaTzad Shmei
Tiltul, one says even though you're moving it from the side it's
still considered moving of מוקצה, Muktzah, and it's a problem. ומר סבר,
U'Mar Savar, and the other holds לא שמיה טלטול, Lo Shmei Tiltul,
it's not considered moving of מוקצה. Muktzah. Now I should say, I
do want to distinguish between two categories. There's something called טלטול כלאחר
יד Tiltul K'Alachar Yad or or טלטול
בגוף, Tiltul BeGuf, you know, which basically means you're not just moving
it indirectly, you're actually moving it with like another body part which
you are like blowing on it, you're kicking it, you're moving it
maybe with your elbow. That type of a thing is allowed on
שבת, Shabbat, important thing to know, that you're allowed to move מוקצה
Muktzah in that very unusual way, even if you're moving it for
the sake of the מוקצה Muktzah object, you don't want it to
get damaged or something of that nature. Okay, so I suppose if
you could pick up the מת meis with your elbows, that would
be allowed because that wouldn't be טלטול מן הצד, Tiltul Min HaTzad,
that would be טלטול כלאחר יד Tiltul K'Alachar Yad with a שינוי.
Shinui. טלטול מן
הצד Tiltul Min HaTzad is when you are moving it with your
hands but you're moving it indirectly, either through another object like here
you're carrying it on the bed, or a classic example is like
I said, you're going for, you know, I don't know, you're going
in your closet for your for your for your
you're going for like the apple and indirectly you're, you know, you're
hitting your iPod out of the way. So that's טלטול מן הצד
Tiltul Min HaTzad where you're moving it with your hand but basically
like inadvertently, you know, incidentally or through something else like this מת
meis carrying it on the bed. And here the basic הלכה Halacha
is the following: that you're allowed to do that לצורך דבר המותר.
L'Tzorech Davar HaMuttar. If you're going for the apple and you have
to like your hand is like pushing the iPod out of the
way, you can't pick up the iPod and move it out of
the way, that's direct moving, but you can go for maybe iPod
isn't a good example, I don't know, but some what? Oh, not
an Apple computer. Okay, forget it. An orange. You're going for the
orange and and your hand is hitting your wallet as you're going
for the orange. Okay, so anyway you can't pick up your your
your wallet, but you can go towards the orange and move it
incidentally or you can sort of move it through an intermediary which
is the case of the מת. meis. Now that is allowed, back
again, that is allowed if it's done for the sake of a
דבר המותר, Davar HaMuttar, if you're trying to get to the orange.
That is not allowed for the sake of, I want to relocate
my wallet. So the basic difference is again that טלטול כלאחר יד
Tiltul K'Alachar Yad with a שינוי Shinui like your elbows or your
kicks. kicking it or blowing on it, is allowed even if you're
trying to move the wallet for the sake of the wallet, even
if you're trying to protect the wallet, if you're just doing it
sort of incidentally as you're moving your hand towards something else or
you're doing it through an intermediary like this case of the מת
met and the bed, then that is not allowed for the sake
of the מוקצה muktzah object, it's only allowed for a היתר heter
object. And that's why this issue is being debated. This is a
case that you're moving the מת met with טלטול מן הצד, tiltul
min hatzad, but you are doing it for the sake of the
מת. met. And that's why there's a debate whether that's allowed. One
says it's still considered טלטול, tiltul, meaning it's moving מוקצה muktzah and
it's no good, and the other says it will be allowed. Let's
just finish this and then I'll take the questions. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, כתנאי. kitnai. This is like a debate
of
תנאים. Tannaim. אין מצילין את המת מפני הדליקה—you ein matzilin et hamet
mipnei hadleika cannot save the dead body from a fire. אמר רבי
יהודה בן לקיש, amar Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish, רבי יהודה בן לקיש
Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish says, שמעתי שמצילין את המת מפני הדליקה—I shamati
shematzilin et hamet mipnei hadleika heard you're allowed to save it from
the fire. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דאיכא ככר
או תינוק, i d'ika kikar o tinok, if there's a loaf of
bread or the infant, מאי טעמא דתנא קמא, mai ta'ama deTanna Kama,
why would the first opinion say no? The גמרא Gemara is working
with an assumption that everybody agrees to that allowance. אי דליכא, i
d'leika, if there's no infant or loaf of bread,
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda? Now, maybe you could
just say he's going to, well, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Obviously a fire is a little different scenario than the sun.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לאו בטלטול מן הצד פליגי. ela
lav betiltul min hatzad pligi. They're debating exactly our case. You want
to move it incidentally on the bed, and
but you're moving it for the sake of the dead body and
that's what's being debated. מר סבר טלטול מן הצד שמו טלטול, mar
savar tiltul min hatzad shemo tiltul, one says it's still considered moving
מוקצה muktzah and it's a problem, ומר סבר לא שמו טלטול, umar
savar lo shemo tiltul, the other says it's not a problem. So
look, it seems like it's that debate. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא, lo, no, not necessarily no, that's not the case. Anytime the
גמרא Gemara says לימא כתנאי, leima kitnai, let us say it is
like a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, you know that the גמרא Gemara
is going to respond by saying לא, lo, no, it's not necessarily
what they were debating. There's another way to explain their debate. When
it says כתנאי, kitnai, it is like a debate of תנאים, Tannaim,
then the גמרא Gemara is going to
actually stay with that. So here it said maybe this is the
debate and it says no, that's not necessarily the debate. דכולי עלמא
טלטול מן הצד שמו טלטול. dekulei alma tiltul min hatzad shemo tiltul.
Everybody could hold that if you move it incidentally that's considered moving
מוקצה muktzah and it's a problem. And again, we פוסק posken this
way if it's for the sake of the מוקצה muktzah object. You
cannot move it with, incidentally or through another item if it's for
the sake of the מוקצה muktzah object, but you can do it
for the sake of getting to something that is a דבר מותר.
davar hamutar. But everybody says in this type of a case it's
moving מוקצה muktzah and it's a problem. והיינו טעמא דרבי יהודה בן
לקיש, vehainu ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda ben Lakish, this is the reason of
רבי יהודה בן לקיש Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish that says you're allowed
to save it from the fire, even though you're clearly moving מוקצה.
muktzah. דחסי עליה, dechasi alei, דאי לא שרית ליה, de-i lo sharit
lei, מתוך שאדם בהול על מתו, mitoch she'adam bahul al meto, somebody
is going to be very anxious about saving this corpse, it's a
relative or whatever it is, obviously they don't want to see it
burn in the fire. אי לא שרית ליה, i lo sharit lei,
if you don't give him some way to do it by moving
מוקצה, muktzah, so you say, oh, I can't move it because it's
מוקצה. muktzah. So what's he going to do? אתי לכבויי, ati lechabuyei,
he'll just extinguish the fire, which is obviously worse. And this is
an important point. We have a number of times by הלכות שבת
hilchot Shabbat where חז"ל Chazal understood that, even for a person that
obviously is normally very observant and keeping all the law, in terms
of the sort of anxiety of the moment or the pressure of
the moment will just do it anyway. And you have therefore give
him a way to do it that's less of a violation. And
therefore here they're going to let you move מוקצה, muktzah, it's better
than the alternative. A what? Take your wallet? Well, the yeah, the
classic example is we'll see later. A guy finds himself outside of
the city and it's about to become שבת Shabbat and he's got
his wallet on him. So if you don't give him some way
of doing it, even if it's a tricky way by taking little
steps and stopping in between, but if you don't give him allow
him to do that, you say no, you can't do anything and
I'm sorry, you have to leave your wallet there. He's going to
say to heck with it and he'll just walk home with his
wallet. So we have to sometimes find ways to allow people to
do it. אמר רב יהודה בן שילא אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן. amar Rav Yehuda ben Shila amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan.
So we said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה
כרבי יהודה בן לקיש במת. halacha keRabbi Yehuda ben Lakish bemet. We
rule like him by a dead body. We have to give him
this special allowance even if normally there is not an allowed way.
And I'll just read to the משנה. Mishnah. The last point in
the משנה, Mishnah, previous משנה, Mishnah, which will a little bit be
taken up in the next משנה, Mishnah, is that if you put
the vessel under the lamp to catch the oil, well you're not
allowed to do it for the various reasons we said—not moving something
for sake of a מוקצה muktzah object or מבטל כלי מהיכנו, mevatel
kli meheichano, etcetera. But if you did do it, or maybe you
had it set up before שבת, Shabbat, you still cannot benefit from
the oil that dripped from the lamp. So אין נהנין הימנו—you ein
nehenin mimenu cannot benefit from the oil that dripped from the lamp.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we taught, לפי שאינו מן המוכן. lefi she'eino
min hamuchan. תנו רבנן—it's tanu rabanan not set aside, therefore it's מוקצה.
muktzah.
מותר השמן שבנר. mutar hashemen shebaner. מותר השמן שבנר—the mutar hashemen shebaner
leftover oil in the lamp, let's say the fire burnt out on
שבת Shabbat and there is oil left in the actual lamp itself,
ושבקערה—or v'shebakara oil that dripped on the plate, אסור asur is forbidden.
That was oil that when שבת Shabbat began was set aside to
be used for burning and for the lamp, so it's something that
you had totally sort of discarded. pushed aside, you know, you know
something that there was, you know that you were not at all
planning on using. It was something that was designated for the burning
of the lamp, so it's forbidden. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מתיר, matir,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's allowed because as we know, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not hold of most categories of מוקצה, Muktzah,
and since right now this oil is usable, even though when שבת
Shabbos began it was something that was set aside for use for
the lamp, he doesn't have a problem and you can go ahead
and use it. Yes.
So my question was the whole thing with the מת meit and,
you know, having to get around it, was that all according to
the position that you can't take something for a מוקצה? Muktzah? Because
otherwise he could have said you can just cover a sudden מת
meit in the place where the מת meit is on and just
move it, right? Or, or, and do we also say that מת
meit is maybe worse because, you know, maybe it's מוקצה מחמת מיאוס,
Muktzah machmas mius, or something like that?
Okay, well without getting into מוקצה מחמת מיאוס Muktzah machmas mius and
those categories which we'll get to pretty soon, I would say the
following. There's a difference. The case of אין כלי ניטל אלא לצורך
דבר הניטל ein kli nital ela l'tzorech davar hanital is that you're
basically moving something not מוקצה. Muktzah. And even if you're moving something
not מוקצה, Muktzah, according to that opinion which we don't פסקן pasken
like, I'll just get to in a minute how we פסקן, pasken,
even if you're moving something not מוקצה, Muktzah, it can only be
moved for a legitimate reason. And it cannot be moved and to
move it for the sake of a מוקצה Muktzah object is not
legitimate. That's not comparable to the מת. meit. The מת meit is
you're actually moving something מוקצה Muktzah itself. So that's number one. So
it's not relevant to the question of the issue of can you
move something for the sake of a מוקצה Muktzah object. Here you're,
that's can you move a non-מוקצה Muktzah object for the sake of
a מוקצה Muktzah object? Now, what can you move a מוקצה Muktzah
object for? Nothing. And actually this gets me into an important principle
which I want to use, say now because we're going to get
into, like we're already into a heart of מוקצה Muktzah discussions and
I want to lay out some important categories of מוקצה Muktzah which
you'll tell me at the end, Michael, if I've addressed your question,
but it's important because this is confused. People are generally confused about
this. There are two categories of things, two big categories of things.
Actually when the גמרא Gemara will get to a historical discussion of
מוקצה, Muktzah, you'll see it'll describe this. There's something called כלים keilim
and there's something called מוקצה. Muktzah. What do I mean by that?
I mean a כלי kli can be מוקצה, Muktzah, a lamp can
be מוקצה, Muktzah, but here's the difference. A כלי kli is something
basically that, the כלים, keilim, you've heard the principles of כלי שמלאכתו
להיתר, kli shemlachto l'heter, כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemlachto l'issur. Is this
vessel usually used for acceptable purposes or is it usually used for
doing something not allowed on שבת? Shabbos? So for example, a fork
is a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli shemlachto l'heter, a pillow is a
כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemlachto l'heter. Okay,
a hammer is a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemlachto l'issur. You usually
use it for banging nails. But all those types of things are
things that, you know, are normally in your sphere of objects that
you would, you know, use under normal circumstances. It's not the types
of objects which for some reason you would treat as off limits.
The only problem with the hammer is, is it appropriate to use
a hammer for cracking nuts since usually I use the hammer for
banging in nails? And there we make a distinction. We say if
it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemlachto l'issur like a hammer, you
can use it for its own sake, meaning for like cracking nuts.
You can use it if you need the place, okay, or but
the one thing that you can not do with it is move
it to protect it. I mean you certainly can't move it to
bang in nails, but you can't move it even to protect it
if it's out in the rain. So that's the example I gave.
If you left your hammer out in the rain, find a sudden
need to crack nuts. Okay, that is a type of a vessel
where the problem is the way it is often used, it is
most likely used. מוקצה Muktzah are things which are completely pushed aside,
things which are in a sense off limits when שבת Shabbos begins.
Okay, what is an example of that? Well there's something called מוקצה
מחמת עצמו, Muktzah machmas atzmo, which isn't even a vessel, which is
something which basically has no use under most circumstances, like a rock
or a stick. Now, if you want to make a rock into
a paperweight and you set it aside before שבת Shabbos for a
paperweight, fine. But other than that it just has no use, it's
not a vessel, it's מוקצה מחמת עצמו. Muktzah machmas atzmo. There are
other types of things, a dead body would be a good example
of that, okay? It has no use, I mean you want to
bury it or something, but it's not the type of thing that
you use. So that's a מוקצה מחמת עצמו. Muktzah machmas atzmo. There
are other things which you set aside because there's מוקצה מחמת מיאוס.
Muktzah machmas mius. It's disgusting. We're going to see in a minute
an oil lamp that's a pottery thing, it's oily and it's, you
know, and it's smelly and all that type of stuff, you normally
it's like not a thing you enjoy handling. That's מוקצה מחמת מיאוס.
Muktzah machmas mius. There's מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס, Muktzah machmas chisron kis,
something that's very expensive. Don't touch that vase, you know? It's fragile,
it's very expensive, don't touch it. So that's off limits because it's
of its expense. So those are things, it's not just a hammer
which you normally use for a certain purpose. Those are things which
are called real מוקצה, Muktzah, not כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shemlachto l'issur,
those are off limits. מוקצה Muktzah you can't move for any purpose.
Okay, so when we you hear you can move something, you know,
for its own sake like a hammer to crack nuts, that's only
because it's not really מוקצה, Muktzah, it's כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemlachto
l'issur. But something that's מוקצה Muktzah like a dead body or a
lamp or a lamp that's burning or a lamp that was burning
and all those types of things which are like off limits, those
are completely off limits. You cannot move them for any purpose. The
only way you can move them is issues we've been discussing, if
you basically you kick them or you move them with your elbow
or
it's
a טלטול מן הצד. tiltoo min hatzad.
An example of needing space for a dead body, someone dies in
a hospital on שבת. Shabbos. Right. And they need the space for
someone else.
But in terms of, well look, if it's a סכנה sakanah then
of course it goes without saying, okay, you know, but or even
a חולה שיש בו סכנה choleh sheyaish bo sakanah etc., but but,
but you know, but yes, but again, but in terms of the
מוקצה muktzeh laws themselves, you know, it is not justified whatever reason.
It could be overridden because of חולה choleh cases or whatever, but
מוקצה, muktzeh, something that's real מוקצה muktzeh cannot be moved for any
purpose. Okay, but it can be moved indirectly and there are cases
like here where there's something that overrides. All right, yes.
Two questions. One, why don't we say כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot for
the dead body?
Well,
so that, you know, that's, so you mean כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot
overriding a דרבנן. derabanan. It's a good question. Actually, it's a very
good question. I mean, you know, the גמרא Gemara here finds like
these tricks, but your question is, if you don't have the tricks,
why does it say do nothing? Why doesn't it ultimately sort of
like say like כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot overrules? And certainly the concept,
if you say כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot is לאו, lav, then there's
a concept, if you say כבוד המת kevod hamais and so on.
It's a good question. I'd have to see if there's some discussion
about that. That's a very good question. Yeah, it's a very good
question. Yeah.
Second question is, if you have frozen food in the freezer. Right.
So can you push it aside to get ice cream out? Right.
So it seems like you couldn't because you're just...
Well, to directly handle it and push it aside, no, but you
can sort of move it aside with the back of your hand
or move it back in the corner.
Right. Although there is an interesting some discussion about whether frozen food
is מוקצה. muktzeh. Because you're right, like you can't use it now,
but you know, it is a type, it's basically is food.
I remember you dealt with טבל. tevel.
Right, although טבל tevel is like, it's not even food yet. Meaning
this is stuff that's, you know, that's like halachically fit to be
eaten and it is in the category of food. So that's interesting
question. Is there a difference between like raw and uncooked as opposed
to stuff that is fit to be eaten, it just has to
like thaw out? I am telling you, there's a debate about how
whether frozen food is מוקצה. muktzeh. It actually comes up in other
scenarios. You realize you don't have שתי לחם, shtei lechem, but you
have a frozen חלה challah in your freezer. Can you take it
out and use it for שתי לחם? shtei lechem? Okay, so there
is a question about frozen food. What? Because it's not edible now
and it won't be edible over שבת. Shabbos.
Sure it will. It'll thaw after over שבת. Shabbos.
I don't know. It's a short שבת Shabbos and there's no time
for it to thaw out. Okay. So anyway,
so that's a good question. But even assuming it's מוקצה, muktzeh, find
a way to use it with, you know, move it like push
it aside with the back of your hand. That you could do.
So long as you can do it in a packed freezer.
I don't know what to tell you. So get a stick and
knock, you know, but and and I don't but but you do
it טלטול מן הצד. tiltul min hatzad. What do you want me
to tell you? I don't know. That's the הלכה. halacha. Yes.
I have some questions about this block.
Don't have your ice cream. Yes.
So I know that, you know, this is we're talking about בבלי
Bavli in a certain place and time. But I'm wondering if these
kinds of things would hold in other places and times because of
other considerations. For example,
you're living in an era of persecution and you leave your מת
mais sitting around on שבת. Shabbos. Right. And people say well those
Jews they're...
Right, so that's an excellent point and it's similar, you know, to
the question that Ari asked although Ari was asking more global question
about כבוד המת, kevod hamais, כבוד הבריות. kevod habriyot. You're saying, you
know, what if there's a חילול השם Chillul Hashem issue and other
types of issues? What if it leads to persecution? Yes, so those
types of things definitely, there are always outside considerations that sometimes override.
You know, there, you know, sick people, כבוד kavod issues, חילול השם
Chillul Hashem issues, so there can be those situations that override. But
first you have to know what are the מוקצה muktzeh laws and
then you can decide whether they deserve to be overridden. Right, my
point is, so
are we just learning the
מוקצה muktzeh laws or
are we really learning הלכה למעשה? halacha l'maaseh? No, no, we're learning
מוקצה muktzeh laws. The מת mais a little bit though, like special
allowances they made and the fire and so on, but there's always
other you know, other factors that sometimes can be brought to bear
and sometimes overriding factors. There's no question about that. Okay, so let's
go on now and look at the, I should say in terms
of because we did have two opinions raised yesterday about why you
can, can you move the thing to catch the oil, which one
do we rule by? We do not rule by the position that
you could only move something for the sake of a non-מוקצה muktzeh
object. You are allowed to move a non-מוקצה muktzeh thing for the
sake of a מוקצה muktzeh thing. So if I've got my wallet
or my hammer that's out there in the rain and I can't
move it in, it's my, I can't come up with a legitimate
use for my hammer, it's my wallet, and I can't therefore, as
I just told you, no matter what what reason is whatever, and
it I, you know, I can't reason, I somehow can't pick it
up with my elbows or whatever the case might be, I'm allowed
to go ahead and move something, take a כלי, kli, take a
raincoat and put it on top of the wallet, okay, to protect
it. You are allowed to move something for the sake of a
non-מוקצה muktzeh thing for the sake of a מוקצה muktzeh thing. We
do not rule that opinion. We do rule that you cannot be
מבטל כלי מהיכנו. mevatel kli meiheichano. You cannot take a vessel that's
usable and make it unusable and therefore turn it into something that
is going to hold מוקצה. muktzeh. So to put something out there
that will let's say catch Catch my wallet, you know, that's falling
off, I don't know, of the roof or whatever, or catch the
newly laid egg, and now I won't be able to move the
vessel because it's got the egg or the wallet in it, that
is a problem, that's מבטל כלי מהיכנו mevatel kli meheichano and that
is so we do rule that way.
Okay, ספרא, Safra, so ספרא, Safra, you'd be okay, right?
Yes, and we'll talk a little bit and we'll see cases like
that coming up. So let's now take a look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. מטלטלין נר חדש אבל לא ישן. metaltelin ner chadash aval
lo yashan.
You can move a new lamp, not a candle, a new lamp,
but not an old one. The difference between new and old, new
is one that's been unused, this is pottery. So if it's unused,
it's still, you know, no reason you, you know, it's maybe like
a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur or like I said, like
the hammer, but it's not worse than that. Why is an old
one a problem? Because once you've used it, it gets oily and
smelly and disgusting. So therefore you generally keep it off limits, meaning
of course you're going to use it again when you need to
use a lamp, but other than that, you know, it is not
it is a type of an off limits type of a thing
and therefore it is מוקצה. muktzah. That's the position of the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. Even if it was not being used when שבת
Shabbos began, it's off limits because it's disgusting. That's מוקצה מחמת מיאוס,
muktzah machmat mius, because of disgusting. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, כל הנרות מטלטלין חוץ מן הנר הדולק
בשבת. kol hanerot metaltelin chutz min haner hadolek bashabbat. You can move
all candles except for one הדולק, hadolek, excuse me, except one that
is currently burning. Okay, so this is again רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
who holds very few categories of מוקצה. muktzah. The one thing he
does not let you do is move a burning candle. Why would
he not let you move a burning candle?
Right, it might have nothing to do with מוקצה. muktzah. It might
be if you move a burning not candle I should say a
burning lamp, you'll lead it to either burn more quickly or to
go out. So that'll be a problem about הבערה havarah or כיבוי,
kibui, maybe it has nothing to do with מוקצה. muktzah. Or it
could have to do with מוקצה muktzah and here is a special
category which has primarily one application which is called מוקצה מחמת איסור.
muktzah machmat issur. What does מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah machmat issur mean?
It primarily is applied to a burning candle. This candle is doing
a מלאכה melakhah right now. Okay, and therefore the or burning lamp
I should say, the wick and the lamp that are connected to
it and supporting it are מוקצה muktzah because they're מחמת איסור machmat
issur because they are somehow, you know, connected to this flame that
is doing this מלאכה melakhah on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so I guess
it's an interesting question about thinking about applying to other types of
things like let's say you had what would be an example of
right,
right, well first of all a halogen lamp, that I understand that
why it's different from a מוקצה muktzah perspective than a concern it'll
go out.
There are times you're not concerned it'll go out. But the question
is like what other cases would you have about something that's in
the middle of doing an איסור. issur. I guess you could imagine
like the yeah, crockpot although you know right, exactly. You've got something
that's part of a well that's the same point like why is
your pot not מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzah machmat issur. But somehow what
extension cord right, so it's funny, it's a very like funny category
which we tend
not to apply to other types of things. The גמרא Gemara never
thought of it basically is really just focused on this case of
like a burning candle. So anyway, it could be that רבי שמעון'ס
Rabbi Shimon's concern is not
that you take that the candle will go out, it is a
מוקצה muktzah concern, but it's a concern called מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah
machmat issur and we will see in the גמרא Gemara a נפקא
מינא nafka mina of those two concerns. Yes.
Oh, why would you need to be concerned about מוקצה muktzah for
the to adjust to have the flame burn faster is
no no no, I know, so that's true. Obviously that the moving
it will lead to a כיבוי kibui הבערה havarah certainly an issue,
but by adding a מוקצה muktzah concern it could come also to
make other things forbidden as well. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן Tano rabanan we
taught, מטלטלין נר חדש אבל לא ישן, metaltelin ner chadash aval lo
yashan, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. You can move a new
lamp but not an old one, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says. Because again it's because it's this is something that wasn't being
used when שבת Shabbos began and it's a concern of מוקצה מחמת
מיאוס, muktzah machmat mius, disgusting. And now we have an opinion that
wasn't in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר אומר
כל הנרות מטלטלין, Rabbi Meir omer kol hanerot metaltelin, you can move
all lamps new or old. He's not concerned of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס,
muktzah machmat mius, it's always a question whether he denies the category
or denies the category's applicable to this case, right? Does he deny
the category of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס muktzah machmat mius or just says
this lamp is not in that category? But the גמרא Gemara tends
to assume these are more categorical debates. So he's not concerned about
מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. muktzah machmat mius. So you can move even an
old lamp. חוץ Chutz but what you cannot move is מן הנר
שהדליקו בו באותה שבת. min haner shehidliku bo b'oto Shabbat. A candle
that was lit that שבת. Shabbat. Now this is a very misleading
phrase. If I say the phrase שהדליקו בו באותה שבת shehidliku bo
b'oto Shabbat it sounds like it was lit when? On שבת. Shabbat.
And that's what it sounds a little bit like. And then oh
maybe that's a special problem that you've violated שבת Shabbat with this.
But no, everybody explains that this is meaning it was burning when
שבת Shabbat began, not that it was lit on שבת. Shabbat. And
therefore what even if it is not burning right now? But since
it was burning when שבת Shabbos began, and therefore let's say it
has this category I told you about, מוקצה מחמת איסור, muktzah machmas
issur, okay, it was either associated with a burning flame. I will
say there is those that want to explain מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah
machmas issur means I couldn't have moved it because of the איסור.
issur. I couldn't have moved it because I because it would have
led for it to have burned gone out or to burn more
quickly. So the איסור issur made it unusable. Not that it's involved
in an איסור, issur, but the איסור issur there was an איסור
issur that made it unusable, okay? But it's usually more explained the
first way that the burning flame is the איסור, issur, it's doing
an איסור. issur. So since if it was in that state when
שבת Shabbos began, all of בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, then it remains
off limits for the rest of שבת. Shabbos. And that is the
basic principle that if something is מוקצה muktzah when שבת Shabbos begins,
that designates its status for the whole שבת. Shabbos. So if this
was burning when שבת Shabbos began, it's off limits for the whole
שבת. Shabbos. That's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says. And that's basically
the way we פסקן, pasken, okay?
רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon who was
in the משנה Mishnah now is being repeated. He says you can
use do anything חוץ מן הנר הדולק בשבת, chutz min haner hadolek
b'Shabbos, except for a candle that is currently burning. And that might
be because you'll cause it to go out. Maybe it's not related
to מוקצה muktzah at all. But we'll see about that. כבתה, Kavsah,
if it did go out, מותר לטלטלה. mutar l'taltela. Then רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon says I have no problem. So you רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says if this was burning when שבת Shabbos began it remains
off limits the whole שבת. Shabbos. I say no. While it's burning
don't handle it, but once it goes out, געזונטהייט, gezunteheit, you can
use it. It does not remain its retain its status of מוקצה
muktzah even if it began שבת Shabbos that way. אבל כוס וקערה
ועששית, Aval kos v'keira v'ashashis, but if you have a cup, a
glass like a plate, or an עששית ashashis which is like a
lantern, לא יזיזם ממקומן. lo yazizam mimkoman. That remains off limits. So
that's very bizarre. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon who has such a narrow
מוקצה muktzah and only the candle and lamp and only while it's
burning. Why are these different of these different sort of holders of
oil why are they any worse? So we'll see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara. אבל כוס וקערה Aval kos v'keira and this... רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון... Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon...
Well, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara what the case is.
אבל רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר. Aval Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon omer.
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says, מסתפק מן הנר
הכבה, mistapek min haner hakaveh, once the
once the lamp goes out, while it's burning can't use it. Like
his father says, like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says. But once it
went out you can take the oil from it. And who and
as we know we quoted just a ברייתא braisa before the משנה
Mishnah his father says the same thing. So רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says once the lamp goes out you can move the lamp and
you can use the oil. So that's what now רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon his son is saying. But then he
adds to it: ומן השמן המטפטף, U'min hashemen hametaftef,
the dripping oil, ואפילו בשעה שהנר דולק, v'afilu b'shaa shehaner dolek,
even while the lamp is burning, you now you can't take oil
out of the lamp itself while it's burning, forget מוקצה muktzah because
you're going to cause it to be... because by taking oil out
it's a type of כבוי, kibui, you're causing it to go out
sooner or maybe the actual act of taking is causing it to
the flame to get smaller. But says רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rebbi
Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon, the case we spoke about in our previous משנה,
Mishnah, you have a plate under the lamp and oil is dripping
into the plate as the lamp is burning, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says you can benefit from that oil. The
only thing you can't do is move the lamp while it's burning.
But after it's burning fine, like his father said, take the oil
after it's burning fine, like his father said. And he'll even let
you take the oil that's dripping while it's burning.
No he's not concerned about מוקצה. muktzah. Now let's take a look
how the גמרא Gemara explains this.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so said אביי, Abaye, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
סבירא ליה כרבי שמעון בחדא. Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon sevira lei k'Rebbi
Shimon b'chada. רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar is the son of רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon holds like his father in one regard, ופליג עליה בחדא,
u'palig lei b'chada, and disagrees with him on one regard. סבירא ליה
כרבי שמעון בחדא, Sevira lei k'Rebbi Shimon b'chada, he holds like him
in one regard, דלית ליה מוקצה, d'leis lei muktzah, he fundamentally rejects
מוקצה muktzah
all or most מוקצה. muktzah. ופליג עליה בחדא, U'palig lei b'chada, but
he argues on one thing and he goes even further than him
in one area. דאילו אבוה סבר, D'ilu avuha savar, his father holds,
כבתה אין לא כבתה לא, kavsah in lo kavsah lo, like the
ברייתא braisa we quoted before the משנה, Mishnah, which says you can
only use the oil once the lamp has gone out. ואיהו סבר,
V'ihu savar, he holds, אף על גב דלא כבתה, af al gav
d'lo kavsah, even while even if the lamp has not gone out
you can use oil that dripped from it. Now what is this
debate about? It's interesting that sometimes the גמרא Gemara conceptualizes the debate,
sometimes it does not. What is this debate about? So this seems
to be exactly this question. If the only issue you have with
the burning lamp is you can't move it because you'll come it'll
come to make it burn faster or slower, but basically you don't
hold of מוקצה muktzah at all by the burning lamp, then even
the oil that dripped off should be okay. I don't hold of
מוקצה. muktzah. I just say don't move the lamp, you'll come to
you'll come to make it go out. But if the oil dripped
from it even while it's burning, געזונטהייט, gezunteheit, use the oil. I
don't hold of מוקצה. muktzah. And that's the position of רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון. Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. He doesn't hold of מוקצה muktzah
at all by this burning lamp. His only issue is don't move
it while it's burning, you'll cause it to go out. His father,
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, seems to hold of a category... theory of
מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzeh machmas issur. Why, things that are involved in
the איסור issur somehow become or are מוקצה. muktzeh. So therefore, if
it was burning when שבת Shabbos began, it doesn't retain the status
for the whole שבת. Shabbos. He rejects the idea that it's defined
by the beginning of שבת. Shabbos. But while it's burning, it's מוקצה
מחמת איסור. muktzeh machmas issur. In addition, and that's an additional problem
as opposed to moving it because it'll go out. And therefore, the
oil that drips from it is also מוקצה, muktzeh, because it's not
just about moving it that it'll go out, it's about this is
all designated for the איסור, issur, for the burning lamp. And therefore
the oil that drips remains אסור assur as well while the lamp
is still burning. Okay? So is that clear? This you asked in
the משנה, mishna, why do you need this other reason of מוקצה
muktzeh if you can't move it anyway? And the reason you would
need it is to apply to the status of the oil that
dripped away. Okay? So now what we have is רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rebbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon seems to hold of absolutely no מוקצה,
muktzeh, at least we have no evidence of it, except moving the
lamp because you might which isn't a מוקצה muktzeh issue, it might
go out. His father, רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, seems to reject most
מוקצה, muktzeh, but it says, no, while the lamp is burning, in
addition to the fact that you can't move because it'll go out,
there is a מוקצה muktzeh category he holds of called מוקצה מחמת
איסור, muktzeh machmas issur, and the relevance of that will be the
oil that dripped off while it's still burning. And then you have
these other positions that say, look, even if it's not burning right
now, if it was burning when שבת Shabbos began, that designates its
status for all of שבת. Shabbos. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon rejects that.
He says you don't get defined by the beginning of שבת, Shabbos,
but we rule that way. We rule that the status at the
beginning of שבת, Shabbos, if it's מוקצה muktzeh when שבת Shabbos begins,
applies for all of שבת. Shabbos. And then there's this discussion about
מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. muktzeh machmas miyus. Okay, so those are categories that
have a broader, which is basically how we rule. We do not
rule רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon for מוקצה. muktzeh. Yes?
Or you said they're just debating the מוקצה מחמת מיאוס muktzeh machmas
miyus case because they've all said you can't move it while.
Well, we'll see that. The גמרא Gemara is going to turn to
them. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
אבוקס וקרבא וששי, Avakus ve-karba ve-shashshi, but a cup and the plate
and the lantern, ראויה לזוזה ממקומה, roya d'ziza mimkoma, you can't move
them at all. מאי שנא הני, mai shna hani, why are these
different than the lamp? The lamp when it goes out according to
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is okay. Why are these worse than the
lamp? So אמר עולא, amar Ulla, סיפא אתיא כרבי יהודה. seifa as-la
k'reb yehuda. No, that's not רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. That line about
not moving a lantern, that goes back to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda,
who says it's a problem of like of מיאוס miyus and those
types of issues. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה מר זוטרא.
maskif lah Mar Zutra. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra said, אי הכי, ee
hachi, מאי אבל? mai aval? Then it wouldn't say "however," you can't
move the lantern. According to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, it's a straight
application of his principle. Don't move the lamp, don't move the lantern,
don't move the plate. It says "however," it's in contrast. It means
other things are okay, this is not good. So it sounds very
much as like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says
the lamp when it goes out is okay, but this plate and
these other things, those are actually a problem. Why is that? Okay.
Right. So let's take a look why is that. אלא אמר מר
זוטרא. ela amar Mar Zutra. Rather, מר זוטרא Mar Zutra says, לעולם
רבי שמעון. le'olam Rebbi Shimon. It is רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. וכי
שרי רבי שמעון, ve-chi shari Rebbi Shimon, when does רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon allow a lamp that's gone out? נר זוטא, ner zuta, a
small lamp. דדעתיה עלויה, d'daitei iluvei, because then your intention is upon
it and you're thinking that, oh, you know, it's not going to
burn the whole שבת, Shabbos, and after it goes out, then I'll
use the oil and so on. אבל הני, aval hani, these like
a huge plate, a big container of oil that you're using for
a lantern, דנפישי, d'nafishi, that are large,
לא, lo, they are therefore something that even רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
would agree is off-limits. Now, why is that? It's easier to understand
this גמרא Gemara that the issue is that they were burning when
שבת Shabbos began. So this is the question: does the מוקצה muktzeh
status get defined by the beginning of שבת? Shabbos? We just saw
before that by a lamp, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon said no. If
it was burning when שבת Shabbos began, once it goes out, it's
okay. But what the גמרא Gemara might be saying is, ah, but
maybe it makes a difference. It's not defined by the beginning of
שבת Shabbos if you in your mind had or, you know, would
normally even if you weren't thinking about it, in theory would have
been thinking about the fact that it might burn out and therefore
it might have the potential to be used. But if when שבת
Shabbos began it was off-limits because it was burning and it was
a type of thing that under normal circumstances you would never have
the opportunity to use on שבת, Shabbos, it was a huge container,
you would never have expected that it would go out, then in
that case רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon does agree it gets defined by
the beginning of שבת. Shabbos. Okay. So what have we said now?
We said that one area that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon clearly rejects
is he's not worried about מוקצה מחמת מיאוס, muktzeh machmas miyus, that
the lamp is disgusting. Okay. He is worried about מוקצה מחמת איסור,
muktzeh machmas issur, that it's burning currently. He normally does not say
that something's status is defined by the beginning of שבת, Shabbos, but
if when שבת Shabbos began it was מוקצה muktzeh in a מוקצה
muktzeh category he holds like, like מוקצה מחמת איסור, muktzeh machmas issur,
and it was something that under normal circumstances would have remained off-limits
the entire שבת, Shabbos, was something that you would expect him to
burn the entire שבת, Shabbos, that's a case he would say that
its status is defined when שבת Shabbos begins. All of this is
in רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. We don't rule רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon.
Okay, so we rule that it's defined by שבת Shabbos begins regardless
even in a non-special. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on
to further analyze the other positions in this ברייתא. braisa.
Who is רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? He would agree that you—no,
he doesn't hold—he apparently doesn't hold of מוקצה muktzah at all, at
least not in these categories. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. והתניא, Veha tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, מותר השמן
שבנר ושבקערה אסור רבי שמעון מתיר. mosar hashemen shebanair veshabekara asur, Rabbi
Shimon matir. One minute, we have a ברייתא braisa that says leftover
oil in the in the lamp and in the plate is forbidden
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's allowed. So here we have
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon explicitly saying that even the case of the
plate of a large container of oil, it's allowed when the lamp
goes out. So התם, hasham, the גמרא Gemara says no there,
it's—one minute—התם קערה דומיא דנר הכא קערה דומיא דכוס. hasham kara dumya
denair hacha kara dumya dekos. How big is the plate? So there
it says a lamp or plate, it means a plate that's functioning
like a lamp. It's a small plate. So there רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says it's totally fine once it goes out. When the גמרא
Gemara said before a when the case where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said it's a problem in the ברייתא, braisa, that's when it said
a lantern, a cup, a plate, so then we're talking about something
in that context which is a large container of oil, a large
plate. Okay, so if it's a small container of oil and you
would expect it to go out on שבת, Shabbat, then it's not
defined by the beginning of שבת Shabbat and when it goes out
it's okay. If it's a large container, then you would never have
thought it would be able to be used on שבת, Shabbat, it
is defined when שבת Shabbos begins by the state it's in when
שבת Shabbos begins and even if it does go out, even רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree that it's off limits. As I said,
we rule more strict than רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so even in
the small case, once it's מוקצה muktzah when שבת Shabbos begins, that's
the end of the story. Okay, so now let's see as the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, said רבי זירא,
Rabbi Zeira, פמוט, pamot, which is basically like also like a lantern
or lamp. It's also פמוט pamot often means like a candelabrum, שהדליקו
בו בשבת, shehedliku bo beShabbat, you lit on שבת. Shabbat. Now this
refers to a metal usually refers to a metal type of a
candelabrum as opposed to a נר, ner, which is usually a pottery
lamp. So you lit this on שבת. Shabbat. לדברי המתיר אסור לדברי
האוסר מותר. ledivrei hamatir asur ledivrei haoser mutar.
The one who normally says it's okay, here would agree it's no
good. And the one who normally says it's no good, here would
say it's okay. Now what does that mean? So it means the
one who normally says things are good, תוספות Tosafot says it means
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and it's אסור asur because it's currently burning.
Anyway, or רש"י Rashi says it means the one who said it's
good is like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says that even you know that even
an old case even an old candle is it is okay. He's
not bothered with old lamps. I keep saying old candle, old lamps.
But here he would say it's no good. So why is this
worse than the cases we normally say are good? Because here it
would be that it's still burning. So while it's still burning, even
people that would allow other cases would agree that it's forbidden. But
what's less obvious is the second line. לדברי האוסר, ledivrei haoser, people
that make other cases forbidden would say this is okay because we
have seen that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not hold of מוקצה
מחמת מיאוס. muktzah machmath mi'us. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says when the
lamp—excuse me, we see רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does not hold of
מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. muktzah machmath mi'us. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says when
the lamp goes out you can—if it wasn't burning when שבת Shabbos
began you can use it even though it's old and disgusting. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir isn't concerned about מוקצה מחמת מיאוס. muktzah machmath mi'us.
What we don't know is is he—but he is concerned, excuse me,
but he is concerned when it is burning. He does hold of
מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzah machmath isur. What we don't know is the
flip case. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who's normally strict and holds that
an old lamp can't be used because it's disgusting, מוקצה מחמת מיאוס,
muktzah machmath mi'us, we've never heard what he holds about a burning
lamp. Maybe a burning lamp, maybe he doesn't hold of מוקצה מחמת
איסור. muktzah machmath isur. Right, you get it? We have the position
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says if it's an old lamp
you can't use it, it's disgusting. He never told us what's the
story if it while it's burning. Now you could say it's a
moot point. If it's burning it's old, it's been used once. Ah,
but what if it's something that doesn't get disgusting? Let's say it's
a metal lamp. If it's a metal candelabrum and it doesn't get
disgusting, so does he hold of the category of מוקצה מחמת איסור?
muktzah machmath isur? And now that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
It's saying a radical statement
that yes, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that normally forbids, here he
would allow it. Maybe he does not hold of the category
of מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzah machmath isur.
We're not worried about that. We're not worried it's going to go
out while he moves it.
Okay, so again you know maybe it's dripping or maybe the case
is that it was burning when שבת Shabbos began and it's for
the question about now that it's gone out. Okay, so cases where
you know yes, in scenarios where it's not a concern of extinguishing
the flames. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
למימרא דרבי יהודה מוקצה מחמת מיאוס אית ליה מוקצה מחמת איסור לית
ליה? lemeimre d'Rabbi Yehuda muktzah machmath mi'us ith lei muktzah machmath isur
leith lei? So the גמרא Gemara explicitly
sort of unpacks it. You said the one who normally forbids would
permit. So we know רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says don't use an
old lamp, that's because of מחמת מיאוס machmath mi'us that he holds
like. But he never told us what his position is by a
burning lamp when it's not disgusting and you're trying to suggest that
he doesn't hold of מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzah machmath isur. Is that
really true? והתניא, Veha tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, רבי
יהודה אומר כל הנרות של מתכת, Rabbi Yehuda omer kol hanairos shel
mateches, all metal lamps, מטלטלין, metalin, you can move. Because they're not
disgusting, חוץ מן הנר שהדליקו בו באותה שבת, chutz min ha-ner she-hidliku
bo be-osa Shabbos, unless it was burning when Shabbos began. So here
it's explicit, he holds of מוקצה מחמת איסור, muktzah machmas issur, and
if it was beginning burning when Shabbos began, it's off limits. So
אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela i itmar hachi itmar, fine, you're
right, take it back. Everybody holds of מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzah machmas
issur. For God's sake, if Rabbi Shimon holds of מוקצה מחמת איסור,
muktzah machmas issur, presumably everybody else does as well. So if it
was said, here's how it was said: אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav
Zeira, פמוט שהדליקו עליו בשבת, pamut she-hidliku alav be-Shabbos, if you lit
this metal candelabrum on Shabbat, דברי הכל אסור. divrei ha-kol assur. Everybody
agrees it's forbidden. Everybody holds of מוקצה מחמת איסור. muktzah machmas issur.
And therefore, if it began Shabbat burning and then went out, okay,
so then also it would retain that status, except maybe according to
Rabbi Shimon. But if it was burning now or began Shabbat when
it was burning, everybody holds of מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah machmas issur
and it remains forbidden all Shabbat, except Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon as
Michael points out. Right, well that's true, not Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon.
לא הדליקו עליה, Lo hidliku aleha, if it was not burning when
Shabbat began, דברי הכל מותר, divrei ha-kol mutar, then everybody agrees it's
okay because it's not disgusting. So this metal candelabrum is not disgusting.
If it was not burning when Shabbat began, it's okay. If it
was, then that's מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah machmas issur which everybody agrees
to and is forbidden all Shabbat, except Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon as
Michael points out. Okay, so now we've got a lot of nice
categories: מוקצה מחמת מיאוס muktzah machmas miyus which is debated—by the way,
we פסקן pasken that category of מוקצה מחמת מיאוס—okay, muktzah machmas miyus
מוקצה מחמת איסור muktzah machmas issur which is primarily this issue of
the lamp because it's doing an איסור, issur, maybe because it's אסור
assur to move, which everybody agrees to, and the only debate is
is it defined when Shabbat begins? Rabbi Shimon says no, if it
might go out on Shabbat, the other opinions say yes. And again,
we פסקן לחומרא pasken le-chumra and we say yes, if it's מוקצה
muktzah when Shabbat begins, that's its status for the whole Shabbat. Now
I should say, by the way, that the flip is not true.
If something is not מוקצה muktzah when Shabbat begins, it can still
become מוקצה muktzah on Shabbat if it becomes unusable. And that's a
case like a vessel breaking or we had the catching of the
egg in
the, you know, in
the vessel, the person dying.
If things change, it will be מוקצה. muktzah. But its status won't
last for all of the rest of Shabbat. The idea of a
status lasting is only when Shabbat begins. So if something new happens
on Shabbat, it can become מוקצה, muktzah, but only as long as
that new reality applies. So like if the egg that got caught
in the vessel, once the egg is removed from the vessel, the
vessel goes back to being okay. And that's a principle called אין
מוקצה לחצי שבת. ein muktzah le-chatzi Shabbos. Okay, you can't—the מוקצה muktzah
status does not—cannot last if it began in the middle of Shabbat.
It will be מוקצה muktzah for the time the problem is there,
but once that—if that problem is removed, it'll revert to being okay.
And we're going to see a little bit about this as we
now continue. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
רב
יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, מיטה שייחדה למעות, mita
she-yichada le-ma'os, אסור לטלטלה. assur le-taltela. If you have a bed that
somehow you decided "I'm going to use that bed for money, for
storing my money," you know, talk about keeping your money under your
mattress. I mean it's a bizarre scenario because the גמרא Gemara is
literally talking about a bed, we'll see later that it's not a
normal use for a bed, but you've decided that you're going to
store your money in that bed, you're not going to sleep on
it, it's going to be used for your money drawer somehow, your
money, I don't know, pot, whatever, you know, your money bed. Anyway,
so אסור לטלטלה, assur le-taltela, you can't move it even if you
didn't put money on it yet and even if there's no money
on it now. Why? Because it's designated for this use. So תוספות
Tosafos says how is it any worse than a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור,
kli she-melachto le-issur, like a hammer? So fine, it's designated to use
in an אסור assur way, but how's it different than a hammer?
So תוספות Tosafos says there are some things that are a hammer,
even though it's primarily used for cracking nuts, you know, there's always
a possibility you'll use it for something else. But the גמרא Gemara
imagines that there are some things that you would never use for
another purpose and are completely off-limits. Okay, so for example, you might
remember before תוספות Tosafos reminds us of the discussion before about the
trumpet. Nobody's going to use a trumpet for like cracking nuts, you
know, or for doing something else, but you only play with your
trumpet. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that if you're only going to
use your bed for this money, that becomes like completely off-limits. But
the חידוש chiddush is even if you have yet to use it
even once. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מיתיבי רב
נחמן בר יצחק, Meisivei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so רב נחמן בר
יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asked on this: we say מטלטלין נר
חדש אבל לא ישן, metaletelin ner chadash aval lo yashan, you can
move a new lamp but not an old one. Well, what's a
new lamp? Why do you make a lamp? Why do you go
to the store and buy a lamp? A lamp is made to
use
for—for lighting. So therefore, it's at least as good as the bed
which is not its normal use, but you designated it. Well, for
God's sake, a lamp is made for this, and even so, if
it hasn't been used yet, no problem. So how is the bed
designated for money worse than a lamp that's made for lighting which
isn't a problem if it has yet to be used? So the
גמרא Gemara says ומה נר—what's u-ma ner the story by נר, ner,
so you didn't think we were going to finish today—I knew what
was on side B—ומה נר, u-ma ner,
what's the story by a lamp, דלהכי עבידא, de-lahachi avida, that was
made for that purpose, כי לא הדליק בה, ki lo hidlik bah,
if you've yet to use it, שרי לטלטולי, shari le-tultulei, you're allowed
to move; מיטה דלאו להכי עבידא, mita de-lav lahachi avida, a bed
that's normally not made for holding money... לא כל שכן lo kol
sheken isn't it certain that unless you've used it it does not
get a new status? So אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר ela i
itmar hachi itmar fine, if it was said here's how it was
said: אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מטה
שייחדה למעות mita sheyichada lemaot if you've designated it for use of
money, then it depends. הניח עליה מעות hiniach aleha maot if you
actually
began employing it in that use, you put the money on it,
so now it is really a money bed, it's changed its status,
it was actually used that way, אסור לטלטלה assur letaltela you cannot
move it on Shabbos even if the money is not on it
right now. Meaning once it gets that identity, it becomes like this
off-limits bed and you can't move it on Shabbos even if the
money is not on it. So designating it is not enough, it
has to be put to use. Once it's put to use, it's
like the trumpet, it's off-limits and therefore even if the money is
not on it, you can't move it on Shabbos. לא הניח עליה
מעות lo hiniach aleha maot if you have yet to put money
on it, מותר לטלטלה mutar letaltela then you can move it because
it's like the case of the lamp that you have yet to
use, it does not yet get its status and identity, so your
planning has no relevance and it's just a bed and you can
move it. Okay, so if you want to change its status you
have to designate it and begin to use it. לא ייחדה למעות
lo yichada lemaot now let's say you did not designate it,
then it depends. So the first case is you designated it and
a difference before, after you used it and before you used it.
Designating plus using changes its status, before using it retains its old
status. Let's say you didn't designate, then יש עליה מעות yesh aleha
maot if when Shabbos began there was money on the bed or
there's money on the bed right now, אסור לטלטלה assur letaltela you
cannot move it. אין עליה מעות ein aleha maot if there's no
money on it, מותר לטלטלה mutar letaltela you can move it, והוא
שלא היו עליה בין השמשות v'hu shelo hayu aleha bein hashmashot and
here we get what was implicit before, here we get it spelled
out explicit, the status beginning when Shabbos begins, as long as the
money was not on it when Shabbos begins. So let me step
out and tell you paraphrase what we just said. Will this bed
become a money bed and totally change its identity and be totally
off-limits? Only in a scenario where you designated it and began using
it. Other than that it never becomes a money bed per se,
but there is a way this bed could be a problem if
it is a בסיס basis a supporter for מוקצה muktzah something that
is holding up מוקצה. muktzah. So that's true if there's money on
it. If there's no money on it, then it's totally fine. However,
if there was money on it when Shabbos began, בין השמשות bein
hashmashot then it gets its identity as a בסיס basis as a
supporter and it remains off-limits even if now there is no longer
money. So here we are getting this concept of a בסיס basis
a supporter for מוקצה muktzah and how that's a problem if it
happens in the middle of Shabbos while that state of affairs is
true, but it's also a problem if that's the status it was
in when Shabbos begins, then it will retain that status even if
the money goes off later. Okay. Yes?
So I can't sleep on my bed now if I accidentally left
money on it, if it was on בין השמשות? bein hashmashot?
Well, not if you accidentally left money. The thing and תוספות Tosafot
asks why we're not discussing this point, but this is one of
the criteria for something to become a בסיס basis is only if
the מוקצה muktzah thing was intentionally placed on on that on that
thing. So if you accidentally dropped some quarters on your bed, right,
then that's not the issue. If you actually said I'm leaving my
wallet here and then when Shabbos began you had forgotten that you
did it, then it is a בסיס. basis. So it doesn't mean
you have to intentionally do it for the sake of Shabbos or
right before Shabbos, but when you put the object on the bed
or on the בסיס basis you have to be intentionally placing the
object there.
So if I put my wallet on there בין השמשות bein hashmashot
but I was going to move it before בין השמשות bein hashmashot
but I forgot to.
Right, that
yes, I'll have to get back to you about that. Okay.
Does the money have to be off the bed though or can
you just can you just ignore the money and sleep on the
bed?
If the bed's a בסיס basis if it is a בסיס. basis.
It's not a בסיס. basis.
Well, if the money is currently on the bed then it is
a בסיס. basis.
But let's say you forgot it.
Oh you forgot it so it's not a בסיס, basis, right.
So right which by the way תוספות Tosafot says how did the
money get on the bed on Shabbos and become a בסיס basis
on Shabbos, who's intentionally putting money on the bed on Shabbos? תוספות
Tosafot says well maybe a non-Jew. Okay, so anyway all right. But
yes, it only becomes a בסיס basis if it's intentionally put there.
So you're saying what if it's not intentionally put there and it's
not a בסיס? basis? Yes, sleep on the bed. If you happen
to move the coins it's טלטול בגוף taltul b'guf טלטול מן הצד
taltul min hatzad and it's okay. Now the other thing I should
mention though is is an interesting question that comes up. Is it
אסור assur to use מוקצה muktzah if you're not moving it? Right,
let's say the bed is a בסיס. basis. The גמרא Gemara says
you can't move it. I don't want to move my bed, I
want to sleep on it. Okay. Let's say my chair is a
בסיס. basis. Can I sit on my chair? I'm not moving it,
I'm using it. So there actually is a discussion in the ראשונים
Rishonim whether using מוקצה muktzah without moving it is also forbidden. Okay.
Yes, go question.
An animal is on the bed at בין
השמשות.
bein
hashmashot. I didn't put it there.
Right, so then it's not a בסיס. basis. Only if the human
it's intentionally put there by a human. Right, being put there by
another... sentient being that is not a human does not count. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so said
עולא, Ulla, מתיב רבי אליעזר, Meseiv Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
asked on this idea about this whole thing
about this בסיס Bosis case and the money and so on. Let's
take a look. It says like this: מוכני שלה. Muchni shela. Now,
this is a very complicated משנה Mishnah because it mostly has nothing
to do with שבת, Shabbos, and that's what these huge תוספותים Tosafotim
are about. They're also very big רש"יs. Rashi's. And part of the
difficulty is it's not even clear what we're talking about, what this
object is that we are describing. It describes some type of a
box-like thing. תוספות Tosafot says it might be רש"י Rashi says it's
used for carrying people; it's like a carriage. תוספות Tosafot says no,
maybe it's used as a drawer. And then it describes for holding
objects, and then it describes a מוכני. Muchni. What's a מוכני? Muchni?
So רש"י Rashi says it's like a wheel. תוספות Tosafot says it's
not a
wheel, it's a base, or it's some type of a side thing.
I don't know what your picture shows. Often the...
It's a wagon.
Well, he's describing it like רש"י. Rashi. Yeah. תוספות Tosafot assumes it's
basically some type of a cabinet is the basic thing, it's the
שידה Shidda we're talking about a שידה, Shidda, and the מוכני Muchni
either is a big wheel that's attached to it, or it's a
base, or it's a drawer. Okay, so it's something attached to this
big cabinet.
Well, they cut into and made a מוכני לכיור. Muchni lakiur.
I know, so then תוספות Tosafot quotes that. תוספות Tosafot quotes that.
Okay, so you've got this, let's call it a base or a
drawer. בזמן שהיא נשמטת, Bizman shehi nishmetes, if it can be removed,
some drawers can be removed from a cabinet, some cannot, or whatever,
if it's detachable, whatever this thing is, אין חיבור לה, ein chibur
lah, it's not considered attached to it for purposes connected to it
for טומאה Tumah purposes. If you touch טומאה Tumah to the שידה,
Shidda, to the cabinet, then it won't necessarily affect the drawer. If
you touch it to the drawer, it won't necessarily affect the cabinet.
They're considered to be separate items
and not one big item. אין חיבור לה, Ein chibur lah, ואין
נמדדת עמה, ve'ein nimdedes imah, it's not measured with it. What does
it mean measured with it? You might remember that very large items
cannot become טמא. Tamei. And large means that it's forty סאה. Seah.
It can contain like the size of a מקוה. Mikvah. Okay. So
then if you have a wood item like this, a cabinet that's
forty סאה, Seah, it will not be able to become טמא. Tamei.
How do you measure it? Do you include this, let's say door
drawer or base, or do you not include the drawer or base?
So it says if it's detachable, you do not include it. ואינה
מצלת עמה באהל המת. Ve'einah metzeles imah b'ohel hamess. It does not
protect it in a room where there's a dead body. What does
that mean? I mean, the whole thing would become טמא. Tamei. So
תוספות Tosafot says the example is you've got your dresser, it's covered
with a צמיד פתיל, tzamid pasil, with a tight seal, which normally
we hear saves pottery vessels, but if this is big enough that
it's not considered a vessel, it's forty סאה, Seah, it's very large,
then if it has a tight seal on it, everything in it
will not become
טמא, Tamei, even in a room with a dead body. So the
same way something in a pottery vessel with a tight seal won't
be טמא, Tamei, something in a very large wooden vessel that is
not Halachically that cannot be טמא Tamei because it's so large, if
it has a tight seal, things in it will not become טמא.
Tamei. But let's say maybe the טומאה Tumah should go through a
hole in the cabinet. If you imagine let's say you have a
drawer, let's use the drawer example, the drawer is pulled out, so
you've got an opening into the actual cabinet itself through the hole
where the drawer is, so does the presence of the drawer consider
to stop up that hole and prevent טומאה Tumah and everything inside
this cabinet can be saved? Or if because it's detachable, maybe it's
not considered to fill the hole? And תוספות Tosafot says if it's
assumed the hole is not fully filled, if the hole is fully
filled, it doesn't matter, but if there's a little opening and it
mostly fills the hole, so then because it's detachable, it's not seen
as legitimately sealing the hole, and therefore vessels inside will become טמא.
Tamei. That's מצלת עמה, Metzeles imah, it will use to save באהל
המת b'ohel hamess in a room with a dead body. So far
not relevant to us. ואין גוררין אותה בשבת, Ve'ein gorerin osah b'Shabbos,
you cannot drag it on שבת, Shabbos, the drawer or the actual
whole cabinet, בזמן שיש עליה מעות, bizman sheyesh aleha maos, if there's
money in the on the drawer, or on the base, whatever we're
talking about. So תוספות Tosafot says you might if it is completely
attached, then basically you're moving the cabinet, it's not considered like and
this thing is just incidental. But if it's detachable, then it's somehow
more considered like you are moving this on its own terms. You're
not just moving the cabinet and this is a piece of the
cabinet; you're moving both of them, the cabinet and the base, the
cabinet and the drawer. And therefore it's like you're moving a drawer
with money on it; that's a problem. It's moving the מוקצה. Muktzeh.
But who is going to move such big things to begin with
on שבת?
Shabbos? טרחה? Tircha? All right, well, case where it's not טרחה. tircha.
I don't, what can I tell you, it's got wheels on it.
Okay, anyway, so that's what it says. All of this very complicated
case is just to get to the point where it says don't
move it if there's money on it. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הא אין עליה מעות שריא. Ha ein aleha maos sharya. It sounds
like if there's no money on it, it's permitted. Like if there's
no money on it right now, it's permissible, אע"ג, Af al gav,
presumably even if דהוו עליה dehavu aleha בין השמשות, bein hashemashos, because
the only case to not move it is if there's money on
it right now, presumably. If there's no money now, even if money
was on it בין השמשות, bein hashemashos, you're totally okay. So how
can you say בין השמשות bein hashemashos determines the status of a
בסיס basis here if it doesn't seem like it matters? So the
גמרא Gemara says, הא היא רבי שמעון היא, Ha hi Rabbi Shimon
hi, that's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דלית ליה de-leit lei מוקצה. muktzeh.
He doesn't hold of מוקצה. muktzeh. He doesn't hold that the status
is determined בין השמשות. bein hashemashos. Like we just discussed earlier, you're
right, fine, let it be on בין השמשות bein hashemashos status, that's
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. ורב כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה. Ve-Rav ke-Rabbi Yehuda
sevira lei. רב Rav holds like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and let's
just read two lines at the beginning. רב Rav holds that the
status is determined when שבת Shabbos begins. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami
mistavra, that makes
sense, דרב כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, de-Rav ke-Rabbi Yehuda sevira lei, that
he holds of מוקצה muktzeh and he holds that the status is
established when שבת Shabbos begins. דאמר רב, De-amar Rav, because רב Rav
says, מניחין נר גבי דקלא בשבת, manichin ner gabi dekla b'Shabbos, you
can put a lamp on a palm tree, I hope it means
right on a hook on a palm tree or something, some way
it's not going to burn the palm tree anyway, on שבת. Shabbos.
Why? Because it's concerned if you have your lamp there then you'll
come to take your lamp off and you'll be using a tree
and you're not allowed to use a מחובר, mechubar, you're not allowed
to use a tree on שבת. Shabbos. But he says if it's
שבת, Shabbos, you're not going to take the lamp off because it's
מוקצה. muktzeh. So if it was there when שבת Shabbos began and
it was burning, there's no concern. ואין מניחין נר גבי דקלא ביום
טוב, Ve-ein manichin ner gabi dekla b'Yom Tov, you can't do it
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why on יום טוב Yom Tov can
you not do it? Because a lamp is not מוקצה muktzeh on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So therefore, we're afraid you'll come when you'll
take it off and you'll come to use the tree. The key
point being that if the lamp was burning when שבת Shabbos began,
you can't use it the whole שבת. Shabbos. That is like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אי אמרת בשלמא דרב כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, Ei
amarta bishlama de-Rav ke-Rabbi Yehuda sevira lei, if he holds like רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, היינו דשאני hainu deshanyi בין שבת ליום טוב, bein
Shabbos l'Yom Tov, that's why שבת Shabbos is different. It was off
limits when שבת Shabbos began and therefore you won't use it at
all. אלא אי אמרת כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה, Ela ei amarta ke-Rabbi
Shimon sevira lei, if he holds like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that
this lamp can become permissible on שבת Shabbos itself, מה לי שבת
מה לי יום טוב, ma li Shabbos ma li Yom Tov, it
shouldn't matter. So therefore, what have we concluded? רב Rav holds like
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and which is how we פוסקין, paskin, that
a status is defined when שבת Shabbos begins. So this bed, if
money fell was placed on it on שבת, Shabbos, then it's מוקצה
muktzeh while the money is on it. When the money goes off,
it becomes okay. If however the money was on it when שבת
Shabbos began, בין השמשות, bein hashemashos, and it was intentionally placed there,
that status remains for all of שבת, Shabbos, because we rule against
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and
the status of something is defined when שבת Shabbos begins. Okay, and
with that we will end.